Hello, in this task we are going
to practice unification of terms,
and for this we have six pairs of terms here,
and for each of these pairs we need to check
if the terms inside are identifiable,
and if so get the most general unifier.
A unifier is a set of substitutions, which when
applied to all the terms that we want to unify,
results in these terms being equal; if the
terms we're looking at are not unifiable,
so it's not possible to find such a unifier, then
we need to briefly explain why that's the case,
simply saying we can't find a unifier
therefore it's not unifiable is not enough,
but we'll see what the proper
explanation would be in a moment.
So, beginning with the first pair we have two
terms 'g' one being g(s(s(A)), s(B), B) and the
other is g(C,C,s(D)), usually we want to start
going left to right, so looking at the first
parameter in each term first, and then moving on
to the second and so on, because that's how prolog
does it and we kind of want to emulate this. So
first parameters are s(s(A)) and C, so to find a
suitable substitution here you might say "okay why
don't we just change all of our s(s(A)) to C?",
however this is not allowed
because the only substitution
we are allowed to make are for variables, so this
structure s(s(A)) can't be changed, the only thing
we might change is the A variable inside,
but at this point that's not really helpful,
however this is not all lost because we only
have a single variable on the other side,
so we can just switch this around and say we're
going to substitute all our C for s(s(A)). Now
if you apply substitution you should always check
where all the variables are that you need to
substitute, because they might be on both terms,
so on all the terms you're trying to unify, and
you need to make sure that you are substituting
all of them, not just on one side of your
unification. So for this we get
these two terms and now the first
terms first parameters on both sides are equal,
and we can move on to the second parameter.
On one side this is s(B), on the other side this
is now s(s(A)), once again we can't change this
s(s(A)) structure, we could only change variable
A, so the only thing we can do here and the only
thing that's sensible, is substituting
all of our B for s(A). Now the first two
parameters on both sides are equal and we're
left with the third parameters s(A) and s(D),
and at this point we can make a choice, we can do
two equally valid substitutions, either changing
our A to D or chang D to A, let's go with changing
our A to D... and then we have two equal terms,
or rather two identical terms,
and this is a valid unifier,
but at this point, and this is something you
should always do once you find a unifier, you
should check all the substitutions that you have
and see if you can't apply any of these to the
other substitutions, because in this case we're
using the A variable, but in the last substitution
we are substituting A to D so we should just
apply this and change these A to D as well,
in which case we are saving this step at the
end where we need to change all the variables
A over to D because we're doing that immediately,
and this is a better way of doing it basically.
So we have a unifier now, but is it a most
general unifier? A most general unifier is
just the unifier, but preserving as many
variables as possible, and we've done this
to the best of our abilities in this case, because
we've preserved the D variable and this is fine,
we're not doing any unnecessary substitutions
like substituting D to constants, that would be
an unnecessary substitution in this case and
would not result in a most general unifier,
but this is a most general unifier.
Moving on to the second pair, we have two terms,
f(X, s(X), a) and F(s(0), s(s(Y)), Y), so for
our first two parameters we have variable X and
s(0), and since we can only make substitutions for
variables, the only substitution we're allowed to
make here is substituting all our X to be s(0)...
now the first parameters on both terms are
identical and we can move on to the second one,
which is now s(s(0)) on one side and s(s(Y)) on
the other, again the only variable is over here,
so the only substitution we are allowed
to make is substituting 0 for Y,
and if we do this you can see we have a little
problem here, because now while the first two
parameters on both sides are identical the
third parameters are not, because there's an a
over here that can't be changed and there's
a 0 over here that can't be changed either,
and we are out of substitutions to make at this
point so this is for one an incomplete unifier
and these two terms are not unifiable, because
we have a conflict remaining here. Now we might
take a step back and say "okay we've gone left
to right, what if we went the other way around?",
in that case we would see there's an a over here
and there's a Y over here so the substitution we
need to make is substituting an a constant for
all our Y's, in that case we would arrive at
these two terms and the third parameters are now
identical. However now we have the same conflict
we had before in the second parameter where
there's a 0 over here and there's a over here,
so obviously these two substitutions Y to 0,
and Y to a are kind of in conflict and this
is exactly the explanation that we need
at this point, because as the task says,
we need to briefly explain why they're not
unifiable and we can do that by leaving our
incomplete unifier or just deleting it entirely
and explaining shortly what we did, you can say:
"not unifiable because X would have to be replaced
by s(0)", that's the first substitution we did,
"however there are two competing
substitutions for Y, Y to 0 and Y to a, and...
since these can't both be
applied we have a conflict."
This would be a valid explanation and
this would be enough for this subtask b.
Moving on to the third pair we have two terms
c, and at this point we need to be careful
to read these parentheses correctly,
these terms only have two parameters.
The first parameter on one side is this
whole structure of c(b(A,B), s(B)), on
the other side that's c(D,a), and once again
we read left to right, this is going to be
a little more complicated at this point, but
it's going to be simple enough to do I think.
So we have this structure c on both sides so we
can step inside of that, and we see we have D,a
over here we have this b(A,B) over there and s(B)
here, so the first substitution we definitely need
to make, because we can't change this structure
only the variables inside, is D to b(A,B).
On the second one we have a structure s(B) over
here and a constant here, you can't change the
constant, you can't change the structure,
so immediately we have a conflict here,
where these two can't be unified, because there's
no substitution that would make these identical.
So we can remove our incomplete unifier
and immediately say "not unifiable,
because a is not unifiable with s(B)"
or the other way around if you want, so
"because s(B) is not unifiable with a"
and this would be a valid explanation at this
point and that would take care of this pair.
For subtask d we have once again two terms c
and these once again have only two parameters,
so we need to be careful with our parentheses,
this is the second parameter here and this is
the second parameter on the other one, however
for the first parameters we have the variable A
and the constant a, so this is
an easy substitution to make.
Now the first term is completely made up of
non-variables so nothing can be changed over here,
so we need to only look over here and since these
structures are now the same on both sides we only
have constants and variables left, so we can
simply swap them all out in one step because...
well it's just simple substitutions like the one
we did before, so substituting B for constant a,
substituting variable C for constant b and
substituting variable D for constant c.
And if we apply these we
arrive at our unified terms
and our unifier. At this point you might ask
"okay is this still the most general unifier,
because there's no variables left?", however there
were no other substitutions we could have done in
this case, so this, while not preserving any
variables, is still the most general unifier.
And moving on to e, e has two terms p, p(s(A),
h(B,C), C) and the other being p(D, h(D,E), 2),
so beginning with the first
parameters again, s(A) and D, this
s() can't be changed so the only substitution
we can do is changing all the D to s(A).
Which gets us these two terms, first
parameters are identical and we can
move on to the second one. Again we
have h(B,C) here and h(D,E) here so
stepping inside of this, because the h structure
is identical on both sides, we can look at the
first part of that, the first parameter of
this h term here is B and s(A) over there
so once again this s() can't be changed, so the
next substitution you need to make is B to s(A).
Now the second parameter is partially identical,
we are left with the second part of that, so this
is a variable C here and a variable E here, and
at this point once again we have a choice, we can
either go for changing all the C to E or changing
all the E to C, let's go with changing all the E
to C, that's one less step, because we have two
C and only one E so i'm changing the E to C.
Now the first and second parameters on
both sides are fully unified and we have
the third one which is C and 2, this
is once again a simple substitution,
and if we apply that we need to apply that to
all of these C. Now at this point we need to
be careful because for the first time in this
task we have the same variable on both sides,
so making sure we substitute all of them we
arrive at these two terms which are now identical,
so this is a unifier for it. However as we've seen
in the first pair for subtask a we need to check
if we can't apply our substitutions on any of our
other substitutions, in this case we're using C
over here and we are substituting 2
for C, so we can immediately apply this
and change E to 2 as well and now this is the
most general unifier that we actually want.
Finally we have two terms r, one r(A,A)
and the other r(s(B,C), s(s(D,1),1)),
once again going left to right the only
substitution we can make since we can't
change this structure s() here is A to s(B,C).
Now the first parameters are identical
and we can move on to the second,
which is now s(B,C) over here and this
s(s(D,1),1) over there so the first
s() here is identical so we can step
inside of that, and the first part,
which is B here and s(D,1) here, so the only
substitution we can make is s(D,1) for B.
At this point we need to be careful again,
because we have the same variable on both sides
and changing all of them gets us these two terms.
The first parameters are still identical as they
should be, and the second parameters
are now s(s(D,1), C) and s(s(D,1),1),
so we're only left with the variable
C here and constant 1 over there,
so C to 1 is the only substitution you can make,
and that applied to all of our C would result in
these two terms, which are now identical so
this is a unifier and these two are unifiable.
However at this point once again, like
in e) and a), we need to check if we
can apply our substitutions on any of our other
substitutions, and here we're using C over here,
we're substituting 1 for C so we need to change
that and one step further we're using B here
and we're making a substitution for B so we can
also apply that immediately, resulting in this,
now most general, unifier that we want. And
that finishes the last pair and the entire task.